A Guide to the Equality Virginia records, 1972-2008
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Equality Virginia records, 1972-2008
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 399
5.88 linear feet.
Equality Virginia
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Equality Virginia in 2015.
Biographical/ Historical Information
Equality Virginia was founded in 1989 as Virginians for Justice, which served as a statewide, non-partisan education, outreach, and advocacy organization seeking equality for lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) Virginians. The organizational structure consists of members, advisory councils, board of directors, and the executive committee as well as three task force groups: Hate Crimes Task Force, Development Task Force, and Legislative Task Force.
When the organization was founded, their immediate goal was to pursue the enactment of legislation that would ban discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation in all aspects of life. Specific goals included: to reform the ABC laws discriminating against LGBT establishments, increase penalties for hate crimes, amend the humans rights law to prohibit discrimination based on sexual orientation, and fight for the rights of victims of the AIDS epidemic. Materials in the collection document strategies employed by Equality Virginia to forward these goals, including the following: uniting LGBT organizations, educating Virginians, communicating to the media, lobbying the members of the State General Assembly and other governmental agencies, and encouraging grassroot response to legislative initiatives.
The organization has had multiple successes in changing Virginia legislation to include equal rights for LGBT Virginians. These successes include fighting the Virginia Housing Development Authority's "Family Rule" legislation, overturning legislation that allowed the Virginia Alcoholic Beverage Control Board to revoke liquor licenses for homosexual establishments, along with defeating legislation that would ban gay adoption in Virginia.
Scope and Contents
The Equality Virginia records collection includes materials created and acquired by the organization in the course of carrying out its administrative, outreach, and advocacy activities. Materials include minutes, reports, correspondence, bylaws, clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, electronic records, and audio visual materials. The collection is of value as it includes legislative materials and news clippings pertaining to the Bottoms v. Bottoms case, news clippings documenting the HIV/AIDS epidemic, along with clippings of hate crimes that the Virginia LGBT community faced during the 1980s and 1990s. The legislative materials also include the lawsuit against the Virginia Alcoholic Beverage Control that overturned legislation allowing liquor licenses to be revoked at establishments employing or catering to homosexuals. A substantial group of materials pertains to the Virginia Housing Development Authority's "Family Rule" which Equality Virginia led the fight against, defeating legislation that would have kept LGBT families from qualifying for low-income loans. Researchers will find content containing materials for potential research in the HIV/AIDS epidemic, LGBT legal rights from 1987 to 2005, the Bottoms v. Bottoms case, or LGBT hates crimes. The collection also provides insight into the personal beliefs and views held by Virginia General Assembly candidates during the 1990s through candidate questionnaires conducted by Equality Virginia.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Series 1: Administrative records, 1988-2008; Series 2: Outreach materials, 1988-2008; Series 3: Legislative materials, 1972-2008; Series 4: Clippings, 1988-2006.
Efforts have been made to maintain the original file organization. Files are arranged alphabetically in each series and materials within the files are arranged chronologically where applicable.
Gay rights -- Virginia -- Richmond.; Gay activists -- Virginia -- Richmond.
- Administrative records, 1988-2008
  - Annual board of directors retreat, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles of incorporation, bylaws, and organizational materials, 1988-2007 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Board meeting minutes and reports, 1988-2004 (Box 1:4-5, Box 2:1-3)
  - Board resource guide, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Community action teams concept paper and three-year plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, board of directors, 1991-1992, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, response to Roanoke Times Living Gay series, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Virginia Housing Development Authority's family policy, 2003 (Box 2:8, Box 3:1-5)
  - Correspondence, Virginia Tech's removal of sexual orientation from anti-discrimination policy, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Education Fund Report, 1989-2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Education Fund, PAC board meeting reports, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Executive director, legislative, and manager reports, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial report, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Founding material, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Funders of Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Programs directory, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Internal committee materials, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Model release forms, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1989-1990, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pledge packet, general information, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Strategic planning, 1990-2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Tax Forms, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The State of Violence in LGBTQ Communities report, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Voice newsletter, 1990-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Website hardcopy printouts, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Outreach materials, 1988-2008
  - 20 OUTstanding Virginians video, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Action Alerts, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Anti-Hate Crimes and Anti-Violence resources, 2001-2007 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Christian Right articles, circa 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Church Materials and Faith-based materials, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Commonwealth Dinner videos, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Directory of Virginia Service Organizations for Gays and Lesbians, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Equal Rights for Gays and Lesbians audio cassette, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ethical, Legal and Social Implications of Human Genome Research program announcement, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fairfax Alliance for Citizen Equality information packet, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Fighting for Safe Schools in Virginia transparencies, circa 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising and Event information, 1994-1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hate Crimes Task Force program proposals and updates, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Homosexuality Issues Packet by Concerned Women for America of Virginia, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - LGBT Contacts in Southern Virginia, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - LGBTQ Capital Gains and Losses report, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Logo and Grapics discs, 2005-2007, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Major Donor Planned Giving files, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mothers and Others of Virginia promotional information, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - National Center for Lesbian Rights publications and materials, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Network Statewide Conference on LGBT Issues, 1992-1999 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Organizations' newsletter, pamphlets, and information, 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - OutReach to Virginia Public Officials newsletters, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Podcasts Julian Bond and Chuck Robb disc, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Pride Festivals and Summits, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Programs, flyers, advertisements, and bumper sticker, 1988-2007 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Rally photographs disc, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Safe Harbor Domestic Violence Materials, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Same-sex marriage articles, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Women's Voices Forum information packets, 2001-2006 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - WRIR announcements and programs discs, 2005-2006, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Currents McDonnell Interview video, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Vote No on 1 campaign discs, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Vote No on 1 campaign banners, undated (Art Rack: Two banners)
- Legislative materials, 1972-2008
  - Albemarle county schools district wide harrassment policies, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - America Votes, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - American Bar Association draft policy on sexual orientation and adoption, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Anti-Gay Virginia laws, activism, and call to arms, 1992-2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Atlas Project Strategic Roadmap Virginia, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Authority of Arlington County to Prohibit Discrimination on Basis of Sexual Orientation, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Criminal penalties, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Challenging the Christian Right, The Activist's Handbook, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Christian Coalition Leadership manual, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth Coalition Marriage campaign, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Democratic Party of Virginia Election Readiness report, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Final Report on Virginia General Assembly and supporting documents, 1993-1994 (Box 8:7-8, Box 9:1-2)
  - Health, Disease Prevention and Control, Crimes Against the Person bills, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Human Rights Campaign's Civil Marriage briefing binder, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Legislative Packet for Virginia General Assembly, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Legislative Report for Virginia General Assembly, 2001 (Box 9:7, Box 10:1)
  - Legislative Strategies, Campaign to Preserve Family Life Education, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Letters to legislators, corporations, and candidates, 1991-2005, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Letters to senators from General Assembly members concerning marriage, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Lobby Day materials, 1990, 1997, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minnesota Supreme Court, Goins v. West Group, Rhode Island General Assembly act, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - National State PAC Training packet, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Rasmussen Poll, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Sharon Bottoms Case, 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Sodomy law talking points, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Summary of Hate Crimes, 1994-1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Unconstitutional Alcoholic Beverage Control laws and lawsuits, 1972-1992 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Virginia Candidate Information, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Candidate Questionnaire, 1991-2001 (Box 11:6-7, Box 12:1-3)
  - Virginia General Assembly bills, 1995-2006 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Virginia General Assembly session reports, 1989-1990, 1998 (Box 12:5, Box 13:1-2)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, 1990-2000 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Issues and Answers interview on anti-family legislation video cassette, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Warner transition team briefing, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Clippings, 1988-2006
  - AIDS newspaper articles, 1988-1996 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Gay families newspaper articles, 2002-2006 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Gay marriages newspaper articles, 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Gay political issues newspaper articles, 1988-1996 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Gays in the military, religion, and legal issues newspaper articles, 1992-1996 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Hate crimes against gays and lesbians newspaper articles, 1988-1996 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper and press clippings, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Presidential candidates views on gays newspaper articles, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority family law newspaper articles, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 5)